## **Fatih Sayin**

Austin, TX 78729 | (512) 765 3221 | fmsayin@hotmail.com https://www.linkedin.com/in/fatih-sayin/

GitHub: <a href="https://github.com/fmsayin">https://github.com/fmsayin</a> | Portfolio: <a href="https://fmsayin.github.io">https://fmsayin.github.io</a>

### **CAREER SUMMARY**

I am a strategic and multidisciplinary data analyst and professor in research methodology and theory with 10 years of experience in colleges. I worked as a school principal, university department chair and secretary general for 5 years earlier in my career. I combined my 15 years of expertise in research methodology, project management, and administrative experience with creative data analytics methods and gathered the best results. Major skills and expertise: Has an eye for innovation and analytical perfection. Collects, cleans, analyzes, visualizes, stores, and makes meaningful highlights out of the data with the best tools available. Proactively perfects skill sets and deepens experience with the tools VBA, Python, SQL, HTML, CSS, MongoDB, JavaScript, and Tableau.

#### **EDUCATION**

The University of Texas at Austin | Data Analytics and Visualization Graduated in 2019

Ivane Javakhishvili State University, Tbilisi, Georgia | Ph.D. in International Relations Graduated in 2009

Free University of Tbilisi, Georgia | BA in International Relations Graduated in 2000

#### **LANGUAGES**

**English** Full professional proficiency / **Turkish** Native proficiency / **Georgian** Full professional proficiency

#### AREAS OF EXPERTISE

- Advanced Excel Functions: Pivot Tables, VBA Scripting
- Fundamental Statistics: Modeling, Forecasting
- Python Programming: Python, Numpy, Pandas, Matplotlib, API Interactions
- Databases: SQL, MongoDB, SQLite and SqlAlchemy
- Web Visualization: HTML, CSS, Bootstrap, Dashboarding, JavaScript, Leaflet.j and Tableau

## **MOST RECENT PROJECTS**

- 1. Project
- Name: Trends in Austin Crime Data by Zip Code
- **Tools Used:** Python, API Interactions, Numpy, Matplotlib
- **Description:** The city of Austin provides lots of interesting local data sets. We interested in crime data. Base on the data, zip code was the best geographic measure, but also wanted to use demographic data from the Census. We tried to describe each zip code base on four socio-economic indicators: income level, educational attainment, poverty level, unemployment rate. [Team Project]

Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/GROUP-PROJECT-Trends-in-Austin-crime-data-by-zip-code

**Prezi Link:** <a href="https://prezi.com/view/46V1XovwTPcJulr4D0rN/">https://prezi.com/view/46V1XovwTPcJulr4D0rN/</a> (for project presentation)

- 2. Project
- Name: European Soccer League Analysis (EuroLeague)
- Tools Used: ETL, Python, Numpy, Pandas, Jupyter, SQLite, mySQL, SQLAlchemy
- **Description:** European Soccer League vs GDP data set was analyzed. The success of teams has positive correlation with the GDP of its country. Each teams scorers and goals data were analyzed. The results were compared with the country and city's GDP. [Team Project]

Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/ETL-Project-EuroLeague

#### MOST RECENT ACCOMPLISHMENTS

# 1. Name: Heroes of Pymoli Game Data Analysis

- Tools Used: Python, Pandas, Jupyter Notebook.
- Programmed a general python script to analyze the data for a fantasy game. Generated a report that breaks down the game's purchasing data into meaningful insights. **Link:** <a href="https://github.com/fmsayin/Heroes\_of\_Pymoli">https://github.com/fmsayin/Heroes\_of\_Pymoli</a>

### 2. The World Cities Weather vs Latitude

- **Tools Used:** Python, API Interactions, Numpy, Matplotlib
- Coded a weather API python general script for over randomly selected 500 + cities across the world of varying distance from the equator to detect their temperature, humidity, cloudiness, and wind speed based on their latitude.

Link: <a href="https://github.com/fmsayin/Weather\_Py">https://github.com/fmsayin/Weather\_Py</a>

## 3. Rental Movie Database (Sakila)

- Tools Used: MySQL, GitHub
- Formulated a query to program total sales by each store and staff by type of the movies. Most frequently rented movies, top genres of movies that were detected. **Link:** <a href="https://github.com/fmsayin/mysql">https://github.com/fmsayin/mysql</a> challange

## 4. Name: VBA of Wall Street

- Tools Used: VBA, Advanced Excel, GitHub
- Analyzed Wall Street stock market data in VBA script language.
   Link: <a href="https://github.com/fmsayin/The VBA of Wall Street">https://github.com/fmsayin/The VBA of Wall Street</a>

# 5. Kick Start Campaign: The Most Successful Start-Up Projects

- Tools Used: Advanced Excel, Pivot Tables
- Diagnosed and analyzed a database of 4,000 past projects in order to uncover any hidden trends for being a successful or unsuccessful Kick Start Campaign. **Link:** <a href="https://github.com/fmsayin/advanced\_excel">https://github.com/fmsayin/advanced\_excel</a>

#### 6. Web-Visualization

- **Tools Used:** Bootstrap, HTML and CSS
- This is an analysis and visualization of weather of 500+ cities across the world. The main objective was to showcase the relationship of various factors like temperature, humidity, cloudiness and wind speed with respect to the distance from the equator. **Link:** <a href="https://github.com/fmsayin/Web-Visualization.github.io">https://github.com/fmsayin/Web-Visualization.github.io</a>

## 7. Belly-Button Biodiversity: Bacteria Dashboard

- Tools Used: JavaScript, HTML, CSS, Bootstrap, Flask API, SQLite, Heroku
- Used Flask to design an API for the dataset and to serve the HTML and JavaScript required for the dashboard page. SQLite database file and inside of the Flask application code was used for the database as JSON file format, and uploaded Herokuapp. **Link:** <a href="https://github.com/fmsayin/Belly\_Button\_Biodiversity-Plotly-">https://github.com/fmsayin/Belly\_Button\_Biodiversity-Plotly-</a>

## PROFESSIONAL AND ACADEMIC EXPERIENCE

Jan 2019 – Present	Investment Consultant and Data Analyst, Cosmos Trading Inc. Austin, Texas, USA
Oct 2018 – Present	Data Analytics and Visualization Boot Camp, The University of Texas at Austin
Aug 2016 – Sep 2018	Freelance Researcher, Huston – Tillotson University, Austin, Texas, USA
Sep 2012 – Jul 2016	Founding Director of Research Center / Adviser to the University President /
	Department Chair, Canik Basari University, Samsun, Turkey
Jun 2007 – Jul 2011	Secretary General / Department Chair of Social Activities, International Black Sea
	University, Tbilisi, Georgia
Jul 2004 – Jun 2007	Founding Principal, Nikoloz Tsereteli International School, and Niko Nikoladze
	Secondary School, Tbilisi, Georgia